"How Generosity May Help You
Be Happier and Live Longer"
Many things make people happy,
from eating foods to cashing checks.
But alas, the more we experience
some dose of pleasure,
the less pleasurable the dose.
This is what’s called
hedonic adaptation,
how the first bite of chocolate
always tastes better than the last.
How can we sustainably increase the
well-being of the general population?
What about “being good
by doing good”?
Beginning in the late 1980s,
reports began surfacing
of the “helper’s high”—
feelings of elation, exhilaration,
and increased energy,
following selfless service to others,
and then a period of calm and serenity.
The “high” was thought to be
like a post-intense-workout rush.
Some are cynical about
the helper’s high,
arguing that helpers
engage in faux generosity
because of a selfish desire to
feel good about themselves.
As this author put it,
“perhaps it’s no accident that these
naysayers often seem selfish,
grouchy, grumpy, testy, irritable…”.
They deny themselves the
positive emotional benefits
that flow from helping others,
and therefore miss out on
the happiness and exhilaration
that are part of the helper’s high.
Prosocial behavior, engaging
in actions that benefit others,
is considered a bedrock of society.
Whether communities thrive hinges
on the willingness of their members
to cooperate with one another
and help those in need.
The central role of prosocial
behavior is supported by research
showing that infants as young
as three months of age
pay attention to the prosocial and
antisocial actions of others
and strongly prefer prosocial people.
There is also evidence that giving
leads to happiness in young children.
By age two, toddlers are happier
giving away treats to others
than receiving treats themselves.
And if it’s their own treat
they’re giving away,
they become even happier!
And, as we mature,
spending money on others
appears to promote happiness,
whereas spending on
ourselves may not.
For these cooperative
behaviors to have continued
throughout our evolution
as a species,
there must be biological
mechanisms
that sustain these
prosocial actions,
despite their inherent
costs to us as individuals.
When we display empathy
towards others,
we get a boost in the so-called
“love hormone” oxytocin.
Then the high we get from that
can get us to give more,
in a virtuous cycle.
In one study, people were infused
with oxytocin or placebo
and were then asked to
make a one-shot decision
on how to split some
money with a stranger.
Those who had gotten the
oxytocin were 80% more generous.
Kindness may even affect
us on an epigenetic level.
Could a 4-week kindness
intervention reduce the expression
of a stress-related
gene signature?
Known as the Conserved Transcriptional
Response to Adversity (CTRA),
it is characterized by increased
expressions of pro-inflammatory genes,
and the immunosuppression we get from
a flight-or-flight type of stress response.
And indeed, those randomized to
perform acts of kindness for others,
rather than themselves,
significantly reduced the
expression of these stress genes.
So, could simple interventions lead to
sustainable increases in our well-being?
Apparently so.
Something as small as
remembering a time
you bought something
for someone else
can make you feel significantly
happier right after this recollection,
and the happiness runs
in a circular loop.
Prosocial spending
increases happiness,
which in turn encourages
prosocial spending.
And, rather than getting
tired of the same old thing,
in this case,
being kind to others,
people seem to be slow to
adapt to the warm glow of giving.
For five days,
about a hundred individuals either
got money to spend on themselves
or give away to someone else.
Those who got the
money were all happy,
but receiving the same amount
to spend on themselves every
day kinda got old over time.
They started adapting to it.
But those giving away
the same amount
experienced consistently
higher happiness levels
that did not significantly
fade over time.
The benefits of giving to
others appear universal
across age, gender,
and income,
and even the skeptics who didn’t
think they’d be happier by giving,
in fact ended up happier
when they did.
And cross-culturally, too.
The well-being that comes from giving
may be a “psychological universal.”
Based on survey data
from 136 countries,
giving is associated with greater
happiness around the world,
suggesting that the reward
experienced from helping others
may be deeply ingrained
in our human nature.
And the benefits may even
extend beyond happiness.
Conventional wisdom suggests
that self-care or “treating oneself”
is the best way to reduce stress
and promote physical health,
but evidence seems to show that
outwardly focusing our efforts—
prosocial behavior rather
than being self-focused—
may make us healthiest.
For example, older adults
who gave the gift of their time
by volunteering at two
or more organizations
had up to five times
lower mortality rates
than those who volunteered
minimally or not at all.
That’s a massive difference.
And the significantly lower
risk of premature death
was found even after controlling
for confounding factors
like physical functioning,
religious affiliation,
or social support.
So, instead of just hoping
we stumble onto happiness,
why not run right towards
it with open arms—
and do some good for
the world, and ourselves.